Pierre Lecomte du Nouy papers, 1883-1972 (bulk 1917-1949)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Papers of Pierre Lecomte du Noüy, 1883-1972 (bulk 1917-1949)
MS 174
Lecomte du Noüy, Pierre, 1883-1947
Scientific manuscripts, lectures, articles and lab manuals relate to Lecomte de Noüy's research in biophysics; performed chiefly at the Rockefeller Institute, New York, 1920-1927, and the Pasteur Institute, Paris, 1927-1936. After 1936, his writings concern philosophy of science; specifically as it relates to evolution, religion, and teleology.
26 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
French bio-physicist and philosopher born in Paris on December 20, 1883. He obtained his degrees of LL.B; PH.B; SC.B; PH.D; and SC.D at the Sorbonne in Paris and graduated from Law School, though he never practiced. A descendant of writers and artists, who included Corneille, he was brought up in free thinking, intellectual circles and started life by writing short stories as well as several plays which were produced with success. His deep interest in philosophy and the belief that to progress, it would, henceforth, have to be based on science, led to his taking up his scientific studies again under the Curies, Appell, and others.
The outbreak of World War I sent him to the front as a lieutenant in the "Chasseurs à pied" but his knowledge of mechanics and driving soon put him in command of a motor section with headquarters at Compiègne, where he met Dr. Alexis Carrel, with whom he worked in his spare hours on the problem of the cicatrization of wounds. At Dr. Carrel's request he was attached in 1915 to his unit where he remained until the end of the war, with the exception of a short mission to the United States.
In 1920 he joined the Rockefeller Institute in New York as an associate member, leaving there in 1927 to go to the Pasteur Institute in Paris, where he created the first laboratory of molecular bio-physics in Europe. Heisenberg's theory of indeterminism, as well as the laws of chance, coupled with years of work on living matter by means of physical methods, had convinced him that life and the steady progress of evolution cannot be accounted for by modern physical laws and that materialism can no longer be based on science. His articles and lectures on the subject aroused the enmity of the left wing and forced his resignation from the Pasteur Institute in 1936. The title of Director of the Ecole des Hautes Etudes at the Sorbonne did not provide the laboratories necessary to contine his scientific work and after a trip around the world he wrote L'Homme devant la Science which shows that the laws of chance cannot account for life and evolution. Modern laboratories were being built for him by an industrialist outside of Paris when World War II broke out. Conditions under German occupation prevented experimental work and he devoted himself to writing L'Avenir de l'Esprit, published in 1941 and crowned in 1942 by the French Academy. In 1944 the University of Lausanne awared the Arnold Raymond prize for the most valuable contribution to the philosophy of science to these two books and Le Tempe et la Vie (Bilogical Time) which had come out in 1936. This book gave his new concept of biological time differing from sidereal time, deduced from his experiments on the cicatrization of wounds.
Together with his wife, an American, whom he married in 1923, he escaped from Paris at the end of 1942, reaching the United States of America in January 1943. La Dignité Humaine, which developed some of hthe ideas in his first two books and stressed moral and spiritual conclusions, was published by Brentano in New York in 1944. That year he covered 35,000 miles, lecturing for the YMCA and the USO on his experiences in Paris under the Germans. Human Destiny, a synthesis of his three French books was published in 1947, shorltly before his death on September 22, 1947 after a long and painful illness.
Lecomte de Noüy's scientific work can be classed in four principal groups:
1915-1920--Cicatrization of wounds--He established the mathematical formula based on the surface of the wound and age of the patient and could thus calculate beforehand the exact date of cicatrizatiuon and scientifically check the treatments employed to deduce the physiological age.
1920-1926--Absorption phenomena of surface tension--The tensiometer which won a Franklin Institute award in 1923, enabled him to provide evidence of the existence of monomolecular layers which in turn disclosed three minima in the surface tension of sodium oleate and enabled him to clculate the three dimensions of the molecule as well as the dimension of the ovalbumine molecule and give a determination of the Avogadro number in excellent accord with previous ones.
Physico-chemical characteristics of Immunity--The study of thin layers of serum on water led to the discovery of a physico-chemical phenomenon not due to immunization and showed that the serum is constituted of asymetric prismatic molecules capable of being polarized in monomolecular layers.
1927-1933--Experiments made by heating serum at a temperature above 55 degrees Celcius. Showed an increase in surface tension, viscosity, rotatory power, rotatory dispersion, etc. Altogether twelve new phenomena were discovered, proving that serum and plasma are true solutions molecularly dispersed and not colloids as had been thought hereto fore. Most of these experiments were based on new insturments and new techniques, which have since been extensively used in scientific and industrial laboratories. Amongst these figure the tensionmeter, a microviscosimeter, an ionometer for the measurement of pH up to the 4th and 5th decimal points and an automatic spectrophotometer in the infra-red.
Organization
This collection is organized into eight series:
Series I: Family and professional correspondence, 1883-1961
Series II: Literary Manuscripts, 1902-1914
Series III: Photographs, 1883-1947
Series IV: Scientific manuscripts, 1916-1946
Series V: Laboratory manuals, no date
Series VI: Lectures and articles, 1917-1946
Series VII: Scrapbooks, 1920-1972
Series VIII: Oversize material, no date
Scope and Content Note
Scientific manuscripts, lectures, articles and lab manuals relate to Lecomte de Noüy's research in biophysics; performed chiefly at the Rockefeller Institute, New York, 1920-1927, and the Pasteur Institute, Paris, 1927-1936. After 1936, his writings concern philosophy of science; specifically as it relates to evolution, religion, and teleology. Manuscripts present include L'Avenir de l'Espirit, La Dignité Humaine, L'Homme Devant la Science, Expose des Travaux, Le Temps et la Vie (Biological Time), and Human Destiny. Correspondents include Alexis Carrel, Pierre Devaux, charles Guye, Ferdinand Hercík, and Charles Lindbergh. Correspondence and articles provide information about Lecomte de Noüy's association with the American USO from 1944-1945. His plays and short stories appear to have been written from 1902-1914. Photographs are of Lecomte, his laboratory, and his family.
Some materials are in French.
Lecomte du Noüy, Pierre, 1883-1947; Carrel, Alexis, 1873-1944 -- Correspondence; Devaux, Pierre, 1897- -- Correspondence; Guye, Charles Eugène, db. 1866 -- Correspondence; Hercík, Ferdinand, 1905-1966 -- Correspondence; Lindbergh, Charles A.(Charles Augustus), 1902-1974 -- Correspondence; Lecomte du Noüy, Pierre, 1883-1947 -- Archives; United Service Organizations (U.S.); Science -- Philosophy; Chronobiology -- Experiments; Wound healing -- Experiments; Teleology; Biophysics; Religion and science -- History; Correspondence; Photographs; Laboratory Notebooks; Manuscripts; Articles
Container List
- Series I: Family and professional correspondence, 1883-1961
  - Family correspondence: various. 1883-1894 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family correspondence: André (father) and Hermine (mother). 1884-1886 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Family correspondence: school notebooks. 1891-1894 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family correspondence: Sully Prudhomme (School Master) and Hermine (mother). 1898-1907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family correspondence: various. 1895-1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Family correspondence: various. 1904-1910 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Family correspondence: diaries. 1883-1910 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Family correspondence: various. 1911-1916 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Professional correspondence: Dr. Carrel and Cicatrization. 1915-1922 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Professional correspondence: Pierre Devaux. 1926-1942 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Professional correspondence: Charles Eugene Guye. 1929-1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Professional correspondence: Ferdinand Hercík. 1928-1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Professional correspondence: Ecole des Hautes Etudes. 1936-1942 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Professional correspondence: Ph. Lasseur. 1929-1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Professional correspondence: Radio Corporation. 1933 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Professional correspondence: Technicians, Institute Pasteur. 1928-1932 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Professional correspondence. 1920-1943 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Professional correspondence: Charles and Anne Lindberg. 1936-1939 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Professional correspondence: College de France. 1937 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Professional correspondence: War documents and permits. 1939-1942 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - USO correspondence. June 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - Correspondence and death: general. 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence and death: letters of condolence. August 1947-September 1948 (Box 5, Folder 3-6)
  - Correspondence and death: letters of condolence, sympathy, calling cards, etc. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: general correspondence with Mary Lecomte du Noüy. 1948-1952 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: dedication of Pierre Lecomte du Noüy Room, University of Arizona. 1961 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series II: Literary manuscripts, 1902-1914
  - Plays: L'Admirable Experience (manuscript, typescript). (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Plays: Autopsie; La Chambre Maudite; Coujr Double; and Une Experience. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Plays: Fils de Roi. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Plays: Four Corners Bar. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Plays: La Grande Ombre. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Plays: The Great Shadow. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Plays: Miscellaneous and unfinished. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Short stories. (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
  - Miscellaneous literary manuscripts. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Short articles. 1908-1909 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Literary manuscripts: miscellaneous. (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Literary manuscripts: short articles. 1904-1909 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Literary manuscripts: scrapbook (Blue Star Cowboy's Co.). 1906-1907 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Literary scrapbook. 1902-1914 (Box 9)
- Series III: Photographs, 1883-1947
  - Photograph Album. 1883-1947 (Box 10)
- Series IV: Scientific manuscripts, 1916-1946
  - Scientific manuscripts: calculation for Avogrado number. 1924 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Scientific manuscripts: hypothesis on cell structure and cell movements. 1926 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Scientific manuscripts: cicatrization (curves and drawings). 1916-1917 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Scientific manuscripts: cicatrization of wounds. 1916 (Box 11, Folder 4-6)
  - Scientific manuscripts: cicatrization of wounds (thesis). 1917 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Scientific manuscripts: cicatrization of wounds. 1917-1919 (Box 11, Folder 8-10)
  - Scientific manuscripts: cicatrization of wounds. 1935-1939 (Box 11, Folder 11-12)
  - Scientific manuscripts: cicatrization of wounds (Dessins des plaies). (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Scientific manuscripts: crystallization. 1922-1925 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Scientific manuscripts: dessicated serum (photographs). (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Scientific manuscripts: culture of tissues. 1929-1930 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Scientific manuscripts: critical temperature of blood serum. 1930 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Scientific manuscripts: depolarization. 1930 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Scientific manuscripts: energy and vision. 1920 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Scientific manuscripts: immunity. 1934 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Scientific manuscripts: interfacial tension. 1925-1928 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Scientific manuscripts: interferometer. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Scientific manuscripts: ionic equilibria. December 1930-1935 (Box 12, Folder 4-7)
  - Scientific manuscripts: pH. 1934 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Scientific manuscripts: photometry. June-October 1929 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Scientific manuscripts: polarimetry. 1928-1929 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Scientific manuscripts: refractometry. 1929 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Scientific manuscripts: serum. 1937-1939 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Scientific manuscripts: spectrophotometry (infra-red). 1920-1931 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Scientific manuscripts: spectrophotometry (ultraviolet). 1932-1934 (Box 13, Folder 2-4)
  - Scientific manuscripts: surface equilibria. 1922 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Scientific manuscripts: surface tension. 1921-1929 (Box 13, Folder 6-14)
  - Scientific manusripts: surface tension. 1929-1942 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
  - Scientific manusripts: time (physiological). 1932-1938 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Scientific manusripts: true solutions. 1921 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Scientific manusripts: viscosity. (Box 14, Folder 5-7)
  - Scientific manuscripts: whole blood. 1940 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Scientific manuscripts: x-rays. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Scientific manuscripts: patents. 1920-1931 (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
  - Scientific manuscripts: tensiometers. 1925 (Box 15, Folder 5-6)
  - Scientific manuscripts: infra-red spectrophotometer. (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Scientific manuscripts: viscosimeter. (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Scientific manuscripts: miscellaneous projects and photographs. (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Series V: Laboratory manuals
  - Lab manuals, no. 1-13, note and address books. (Box 16)
  - Lab manuals, no. 14-26, miscellaneous manuals and notebooks. (Box 17)
- Series VI: Lectures and articles, 1917-1946
  - Lectures: "Conférence sur Pasteur." January 13, 1923 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Lectures: "La Psychologie de la Science," (given in Montreal, Quebec, New York, and Le Havre). 1925 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Lectures: "Deux Conférences." 1931 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Lectures: "Le Probleème Biologique et la Valeur de Méthodes," (Brussels). June 1931 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Lectures: "Les Cultures de Tissus en Dehors de l'Organisme," (Conférence Sorbonne). 1931 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Lectures: "Etudes Physico-chimique sur le Sérum," (Congrés de Rome). 1932 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Lectures: Discours Radio Forum. 1932 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Lectures: "Une Mesure de l'Activité Physiologique," (Congrés de Rome). 1932 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Lectures: "Communication à la Societé de Pathologie Comparée." November 8, 1932 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Lectures: Société de Sérilogie. December 1932 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Lectures: "Phénomènes Physico-chimique dans l'Immunité," (Rome). 1933 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Lectures: Conférences. 1934 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Lectures: "La Lutte pur la Vie," (Conférence Radio-Diffusée). January 23, 1935 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Lectures: "Biochimie et Biophysique," (Brussels, Congrés de biochimie). October 1935 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Lectures: "Sur l'Unité de la Méthode dans les Sciences Physiques et Biologiques Comparés." September 1935 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Lectures: "Le Temps et la Vie," (Conférence Radio-Diffusée). 1936 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Lectures: "Considérations Experimentales sur l'Adsorption dans les Phénomènes Biologiques." May 1936 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Lectures: 2ème Congrés Philosophie Scientifique (Copenhagen). 1936 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Lectures: "L'Homme Devant la Science," (Conférence Bruxelles). October 20, 1936 (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - Lectures: "L'Homme Devant la Science," (Lyons). November 15, 1936 (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - Lectures: "Adresse au Déjeuner." February 15, 1937 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Lectures: "Les Limites de l'Inférence Léegitime," (Colleège de France). March 10, 1938 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Lectures given in Montpellier. December 9-10, 1938 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Lectures: "Notre Univers et son Image," (Conférence Collège de France). February 27, 1939 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Lectures: "Figures de la Science," (Radio-Diffusée). January 2,18 and February 12,15, 1940 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Lectures: "Le Rythme de la Vie," (Radio-Diffusée en Amérique). April 20, 1940 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Lectures: "Physique, chimie & Bilogie." May 3, 1941 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Lectures: "L'Adsorption," (Palais de la Découverte). June 29, 1941 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Lectures: "Jubilée Devaux," (Bordeaux). July 2, 1941 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Lectures: "L'Avenir de l'Esprit," (Universite de Lyon). December 7, 1941 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Lectures: "Discours pur Distribution de Prix," (Lycée Carnot). 1941 or 1942 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Lectures: Questionnaire pour Radio-Diffusion. July 1942 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Lectures: "Physiological Time," (Annual General Meeting of the American Philosophical Society). April 22-24, 1943 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Series of Lectures on "La Physico-Chimie de Sérum dans les Rapports avic l'Immunité," (Institut Scientifique Franco-Candien). Mat 3-13, 1943 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Lectures: "La France Inspiratrice," (French Institute, New York). March 14, 1944 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Lectures: "L'Avenir de l'Esprit," Alliance Française, New York). March 21, 1944 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Six broadcasts, (New York). April-June 1944 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Lectures: "L'Expérience et la Connaissance," (Congrés Philosophique de Haiti). September 1944 (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Lectures: "Le Parfum de la France," (French Insititute, New York). April 10, 1945 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Printed lectures and miscellaneous articles (bound in one volume). 1925-1946 (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Carrel Mission," (Temporary Hospital 21, Compiegne). 1917 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Principals of General Physiology," by W.M. Bayliss (authorization and beginning of translation). 1918 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "La Biologie Moderne et le problème de la Vie," Revue Scientifique. February 8, 1930 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "A Titling Gas Stopcock," Science. February 1931 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Replacing the Telephone by a Loud Speaker for Measurements Conductitity," Nature. February 1931 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "La Cicatrisation de Plaies en Surface," Livre Memorial Du Dr. Tuffier. July 1931 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Boutaric, Remarques sur l'Etude des Transformations Pouvant se Produire dans les Milieux Troublés," Bull. Soc. Chimique de France. 1931 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Cultures des Tissus," Revue de Paris. September 1931 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "La Bacteriologie Nouvelle," Correspondant. September 1931 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "The Biological Problem," Memorial Libman. 1932 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Response du Comité des Forjes," New Outlook. 1933 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Necessité de la Recherche Scientifique," La France Vivant. 1934 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "La science et la Vie." February 1935 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Lettre à Mr. Harris," Article sur Pasteur. February 21, 1936 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Filtration," (chapter for book on Ultra-Viruses by Lepine and Levaditi). 1936 (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Geistige Arbeit." July 1936 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "L'Organisation du Laboratoire de Recherche." 1936 (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Biophysique Moleculaire et Immunologie." 1937 (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Le Mystere des Colloides," (préface pur la conférence à Mr. Allee). 1937 (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "La Biophysique Moleculaire," Revue D'Actinologie. 1938 (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Consideration on the Study of General Biology in the Light of Modern Science." 1938 (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous articles: Extrait de "L'Homme Devant la Science," Revue Universelle. March 15, 1939 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous articles: Résponse au Questionnaire de "Volontés." 1939 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "La Position de la Culture Japonaise dans le Monde," Concours Japonais. 1940 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Recherche Scientifique en Temps de Guerre," Courrier Royal. 1940 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Paris letter. May 30, 1940 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous articles: Résponse au Questionnaire de Mr. LoDuca. June 2, 1940 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous articles: L'Institut de Recherches de Demain. 1941 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous articles: Préface pour Livre de Ch. E. Gliye. 1941 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Qu'entend-on par l'Avenir de la Science?" 1942 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Evolution et Religion," Bulletin Des Etudes Française. February 1944 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous articles: L'Américan Moyen nous tend la Main. April 1945 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Science and Religion; the Point of View of a Scientist," (for YMCA pamphlet). April 1945 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "A la Recherche du Tempe Vécu..." Revue de L'F.A.L.. June 30, 1945 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Concerning the Rate of Evaporation of Water Through Orientated Monolayers of Water," Science. October 1945 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous articles: Preface à "L'Homme Libre, ce Prisioner," de André Lang. may 1946 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "La Problème de la Vie." (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Cours de Technique de Laboratoire." (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Les Problèmes Fondamentaux de la Matière Vivante et l'Organisation de la Recherche Pure." (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Aspects Mathématiques de Certaines Courbes de Température." (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous articles: Notes pour articles. (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "L'Evolution des Sciences de la Vie," Revue de Paris. January 15, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Le Viellissement," Revue de Paris. August 1933 (Box 21, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Le Laboratoire et la Recherche Scientifique," Revue de Paris. June 15, 1935 (Box 21, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous articles: "Les Mirages de la Science," Revue de Paris. March 1, 1936 (Box 21, Folder 24)
  - Printed Articles, arranged and bound by Pierre Lecomte du Noüy. 1916-1936 (Box 22)
  - Printed articles, arranged and bound by Pierre Lecomte du Noüy. 1929-1941 (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous printed articles, includes articles by Pierre Lecomte Noüy and works dedicated to him. 1926-1946 (Box 24)
- Series VII: Scrapbooks and manuscripts, 1920-1972
  - Scrapbook, includes clippings about his scientific research. 1920-1939 (Box 25)
  - Scrapbook, clippings concerning Pierre Lecomte du Noüy's and the Pasteur Institute's participation in the Chicago International Exposition. 1933 (Box 26)
  - Manuscripts: Surface Equilibria or Colloidal Solutions, includes manuscript, typescript, and figures. 1926 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts: Equilibres Supercificieles de Solutions Colloidales, manuscript only. 1929 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts: Methodes Physiques en Biologie et en Médecine, includes manuscript, galley proofs, and letters of acknowledgment. 1933 (Box 27, Folder 3)